<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title> - sysadmin</title>
	<link href="https://batsense.net/tags/sysadmin/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://batsense.net"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2021-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://batsense.net/tags/sysadmin/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Ideal backup situation</title>
		<published>2021-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://batsense.net/blog/10-09-2021-ideal-backup-situation/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://batsense.net/blog/10-09-2021-ideal-backup-situation/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been playing fast and loose with backups, and I&#x27;ve been extremely
fortunate to have not suffered any serious system failures or data
loses. I recently recovered from systems failures on my Raspberry Pis
caused by upgrading Debian Buster to Bullseye. The outage wasn&#x27;t a
because of a bug in Bullseye, the upgrade modified some parameters
&lt;code&gt;&#x2F;boot&#x2F;firmware&#x2F;config.txt&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; which, for some reason, prevented the board
from booting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also around the same period, my place was being renovated, and the
construction workers had nicked the main power supply lines. As a
result, we were experiencing some wild voltage fluctuations and power
outages. I thought I burnt my boards from either one of these two
things. It was time to set up a proper backup mechanism.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;requirement&quot;&gt;Requirement&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have roughly 3 TB of storage across multiple devices and none of these
were being backed up. Going by the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Backup#3-2-1_rule&quot;&gt;3-2-1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, I would
require at least 9 TB + 3 TB of storage(3*3 + some additional space for
versioned backups --- most backup systems these days are chunk snapshot
systems so versioning is very efficient). But since I&#x27;m broke and can&#x27;t
afford offsite storage, my requirements are down to 6 TB + 2 TB.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-current-solution&quot;&gt;My current solution&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought two 4 TB disks and setup &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.borgbackup.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Borg&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
backup jobs to run at night. I currently have 7 daily, 4 weekly and 4
monthly snapshots on the first disk and the second disk contains 4
weekly and 4 monthly snapshots, and is unplugged and stored at a
different part of the house.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, it should be plugged in at a different part of the house, away
from my server rack, but I neither have the hardware nor the
infrastructure to implement that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ideal-solution&quot;&gt;Ideal solution&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current set up will work in most cases. I live in a calm neighborhood
in a very safe city(not prone to natural calamities and such) but
&lt;em&gt;ideally&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; there should be at least one copy of offsite backup. So I did
some math to see how much it would cost me:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;aws-s3&quot;&gt;AWS S3&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS is usually the cheapest and there&#x27;s probably an adapter available
for Borg&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pricing:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;aws.amazon.com&#x2F;s3&#x2F;pricing&#x2F;&quot;&gt;$0.023&#x2F;GB-month for the first
50 TB&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cost:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; $0.023 * 3 * 1024 = $70.656&#x2F;month&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don&#x27;t like AWS or anything Amazon&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;tarsnap&quot;&gt;Tarsnap&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tarsnap is developed by &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.daemonology.net&#x2F;blog&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Dr. Colin
Percival&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and is quite popular.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pricing:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.tarsnap.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;$0.25&#x2F;GB-month + $0.25&#x2F;GB
bandwidth&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cost:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; $0.25 * 3 * 1024 = $768&#x2F;month + bandwidth costs&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And is also quite expensive!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&#x27;t afford either of these solutions. My current setup set cost me
roughly ₹16,000 or $220 or the two months worth of AWS rent. Which is
ridiculous. So here&#x27;s my proposal:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the internet becomes more diverse and more decentralised, home
servers will become a common thing. This means more folks, like myself,
will be on the lookout for cheap backup and failover solutions.
Normally, these home servers won&#x27;t be at 100% utilization(I&#x27;m currently
at 20% across the fleet) so forming rings of trust among friends and
family will be mutually beneficial. This way, the participants within
the ring can rely on each other&#x27;s facilities for backups and
failover situations for a fraction of what a cloud-based solution would
cost.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there should be proper measures taken to prevent unauthorized
access and trespassing, but they are implementation details.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>My Matrix (mis)adventures</title>
		<published>2020-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2020-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://batsense.net/blog/26-12-2020-matrix-certificate-error/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://batsense.net/blog/26-12-2020-matrix-certificate-error/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Matrix is probably the largest federated network in production (Mastadon
might be close). I run an instance at https:&#x2F;&#x2F;matrix.batsense.net and I
absolutely love it. It was also the project that got me into the whole
decentralization thing. I loved the idea that I could run a server that
can play along with a bunch of other servers that are run by different
parties and they would all somehow magically work!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;error&quot;&gt;Error&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deployment was fairly straight forward, the project&#x27;s README
files were sufficiently detailed but after about six months of running
the server, my instance broke! The federation was no longer working. I
could still chat with people that are on my own server but I could
interact with rooms on other servers or even on matrix.org. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial error massages were vague. The client complained that it had
hit some JSON related error. So I went to look for solutions on the
project&#x27;s issue tracker. There was an open issue that said that when the
person started doing IPv6 DNS lookups, their instance broke. This was
also the time when my ISP moved us to IPv6 lookups so I figured that was
what was causing problems. At this time, I wasn&#x27;t really using matrix
that much so it didn&#x27;t bother me. I figured, eventually, massive project
such as matrix might roll out a patch. Several weeks and several updates
later, the issue still persisted. So I tried my hands at it once again. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;diagnosis&quot;&gt;Diagnosis&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, decentralization is complicated. Some matrix dev on Hackernews
remarked that building a decentralized system is six times harder than
building a centralized system. The bug that I was experiencing, wasn&#x27;t
really a bug. I misdiagnosed it to be one in the first place. I use
Let&#x27;s encrypt for TLS and their certs are valid for a maximum of three
months. So when I hit that &amp;quot;bug&amp;quot;, I was through two cycles and was
beginning the third. Synapse, the matrix homeserver variant that I run,
listens on two ports: one for regular client-server interactions and the
other for federation. The client-server port is proxied by an Nginx
instance so all TLS stuff is delegated by the Nginx instance. The
federation port, however, is directly exposed and all TLS stuff is
handled by Synapse itself. That means Synapse is configured to read and
do TLS stuff with the TLS certs. That means, my stupid self has two
copies of the same TLS cert at two places. Now you could quickly see how
stupid this is and the problems that it could cause. During the third
cycle, I didn&#x27;t refresh Synapse&#x27;s copy of the certs. It was using stale
certs. TLS is mandatory for federation in matrix. So naturally, my
federation was broken!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;lessons-learned&quot;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am stupid&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintain sysadmin notes to record all quirks of the systems that you
administer&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build simpler services: The more the number of levers to pull on, the
more likely someone is going to screw up. The second port for
federation feels necessary. It is a HTTP endpoint so I don&#x27;t see why
it needs to be separated. It could&#x27;ve simply be scoped differently.
That way, the maintenance and deployment complexity can be
significantly reduced. In this case, firewall rules can become simpler
and the federation stuff will be handled by the Nginx instance itself. &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But seriously, I should have maintained notes. Three months  without
federation over a stupid error is nuts.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
