<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title> - Fediverse</title>
	<link href="https://batsense.net/tags/fediverse/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://batsense.net"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2022-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://batsense.net/tags/fediverse/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>I&#x27;m on the Fediverse!</title>
		<published>2022-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://batsense.net/blog/im-on-the-fediverse/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://batsense.net/blog/im-on-the-fediverse/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;and I have ideas for it. Well, they are more like opinions, really.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently launched a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gts.batsense.net&#x2F;&quot;&gt;GotoSocial&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
instance to join
the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Fediverse&quot;&gt;Fediverse&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I was very apprehensive about re-joining the social media
because I struggled with Social media addition from middle school
through high school. It was toxic, I found myself spending irrationally
long amounts of time on it. So starting 2018, I began to slowly reduce
and delete my accounts on all the services that I used at that time.
It took a lot of effort but I finally did it: to me, social networking
after that meant ringing up a friend or meeting them IRL.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;joining-fediverse&quot;&gt;Joining Fediverse&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, very apprehensive. I appreciate that technology connects people
from across the world. I met a lot of kind, interesting, and generally
nice people from around the world on the Internet even after I quit
social media.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These people are usually from forums, chartrooms, and emails &amp;amp;#8212 all
platforms that take effort to participate in. One has to be thoughtful and
articulate their communications to engage in such platforms. But the social media
is a cheat code: all one has to do is come up with a witty remark or a
clever comeback to have a good time on there!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to join the Fediverse since I&#x27;m working on
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;forgeflux.org&quot;&gt;ForgeFlux&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a project that is based on the
methods and technology that powers the Fediverse to make software
development collaboration tools better represent real world scenarios
— essentially using social media tech to make the programming social media.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so the GotoSocial instance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-impressions-it-is-different&quot;&gt;First Impressions: It is different!&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My biggest concern with modern tech is being unmindful during the time I
spend with it. In this regard, GotoSocial is very refreshing. GotoSocial
doesn&#x27;t show posts that are older than your account(it&#x27;s either that or
my instance is misconfigured). Also, it doesn&#x27;t have recommendations
widgets. Which is nice. I mostly followed people that I already knew from
other channels and follow people that my following interact with and
interest me &amp;amp;#8212 closely mimicking meeting new folks IRL.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-i-am-still-concerned&quot;&gt;But I am still concerned&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I&#x27;m temporarily shielded from the effects of social media because
I&#x27;m new on there, I can see how following large amounts of people would
snowball into creating a very lengthy, frequently updating feed. I hope
social media creators recognize that they are building tools to help
people catch up with their friends and not necessarily helping them
being constantly on top of what&#x27;s happening in their friends&#x27; lives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would say that frequent updates will help information reach people
in a timely fashion but that isn&#x27;t entirely accurate: if there was an
emergency, I would be making a phone call or use some other means of
highly real-time technology that requires absolute engagement from all
involved parties than post on social media and hope that it reaches and
grabs the attention of all concerned parties in a timely fashion.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I propose feed updates only be made in fixed durations. By updates, I
refer to downloading the posts created by the people I follow and
uploading my newly created posts to other people&#x27;s feeds. This way, we
will only be catching up with each other rather than anxiously scrolling
and constantly refreshing for new updates.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
