<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title> - personal</title>
	<link href="https://batsense.net/tags/personal/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://batsense.net"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2023-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://batsense.net/tags/personal/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Social responsibility and basic needs</title>
		<published>2023-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://batsense.net/blog/14-06-2023-social-responsibility-and-basic-needs/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://batsense.net/blog/14-06-2023-social-responsibility-and-basic-needs/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As social creatures, our responsibility and our needs
don&#x27;t just stop at taking care of ourselves. Being nice integral to our
growth and the well-being of our society. So to say that humans need only
leisure and the ability to engage in creative pursuits to sustain
themselves is only partly true.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need opportunities and the privilege to exercise compassion. Those of
us that are fortunate enough to have enough capital to become
self-reliant must also aim to be a little more than self-sustaining.
So that we can help those in need. It doesn&#x27;t have to be a lot, but
creating a positive, strong, meaningful impact in someone&#x27;s life is
critical to reconnect with our humanity and truly realise what it is
like to be human.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Is privacy really possible?</title>
		<published>2022-09-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-09-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://batsense.net/blog/03-08-2022-is-privacy-really-possible/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://batsense.net/blog/03-08-2022-is-privacy-really-possible/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My mind is a mess. Deep, focused thinking is rare. I have discovered that writing helps. Writing on paper, that is. I&#x27;m environmentally conscious, so I use my computer and only fallback to paper, when I feel like it is insufficient. Or when the thought is too intimate. Digital is scary, it is easy to spy computer activity than real life. But the physical environment is not safe either. Notes can be leaked, journals read and secrets exposed. So I briefly considered getting a cigarette lighter: burn the note as soon as it is written and has helped me gain clarity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But is that private enough? What if we invent a gizmo to recover paper from its ashes. Chemistry tells it is impossible but for the sake of this argument, &lt;em&gt;what if?&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; Or what if we invent time travel tech to go back and read the note before it was burnt?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So writing notes isn&#x27;t safe. That&#x27;s okay, I will hold secrets in my head. But if what we invent mind reading tech? It will threaten our thoughts too. Combine that with time travel and the threat becomes eternal.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is scary, and it seems like there is no privacy even in the seemingly safe cocoon of one&#x27;s own mind. But it is far from the truth. In fact, this is one of the reasons why privacy should be more strongly be pursued. We must recognise that thoughts are worthless and inconsequential until they are acted upon. It is through thoughts and in collectives through discussion, will we be able to figure out what&#x27;s right and what isn&#x27;t.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So please don&#x27;t spy and invade someone&#x27;s privacy. It doesn&#x27;t matter if you are a programmer or just a normal person, respect the other person&#x27;s privacy. Don&#x27;t read stuff that isn&#x27;t meant for you. Leave us alone and we can all have privacy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>I&#x27;m on the Fediverse!</title>
		<published>2022-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://batsense.net/blog/im-on-the-fediverse/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://batsense.net/blog/im-on-the-fediverse/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;and I have ideas for it. Well, they are more like opinions, really.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently launched a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gts.batsense.net&#x2F;&quot;&gt;GotoSocial&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
instance to join
the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Fediverse&quot;&gt;Fediverse&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I was very apprehensive about re-joining the social media
because I struggled with Social media addition from middle school
through high school. It was toxic, I found myself spending irrationally
long amounts of time on it. So starting 2018, I began to slowly reduce
and delete my accounts on all the services that I used at that time.
It took a lot of effort but I finally did it: to me, social networking
after that meant ringing up a friend or meeting them IRL.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;joining-fediverse&quot;&gt;Joining Fediverse&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, very apprehensive. I appreciate that technology connects people
from across the world. I met a lot of kind, interesting, and generally
nice people from around the world on the Internet even after I quit
social media.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These people are usually from forums, chartrooms, and emails &amp;amp;#8212 all
platforms that take effort to participate in. One has to be thoughtful and
articulate their communications to engage in such platforms. But the social media
is a cheat code: all one has to do is come up with a witty remark or a
clever comeback to have a good time on there!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to join the Fediverse since I&#x27;m working on
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;forgeflux.org&quot;&gt;ForgeFlux&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a project that is based on the
methods and technology that powers the Fediverse to make software
development collaboration tools better represent real world scenarios
— essentially using social media tech to make the programming social media.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so the GotoSocial instance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-impressions-it-is-different&quot;&gt;First Impressions: It is different!&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My biggest concern with modern tech is being unmindful during the time I
spend with it. In this regard, GotoSocial is very refreshing. GotoSocial
doesn&#x27;t show posts that are older than your account(it&#x27;s either that or
my instance is misconfigured). Also, it doesn&#x27;t have recommendations
widgets. Which is nice. I mostly followed people that I already knew from
other channels and follow people that my following interact with and
interest me &amp;amp;#8212 closely mimicking meeting new folks IRL.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-i-am-still-concerned&quot;&gt;But I am still concerned&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I&#x27;m temporarily shielded from the effects of social media because
I&#x27;m new on there, I can see how following large amounts of people would
snowball into creating a very lengthy, frequently updating feed. I hope
social media creators recognize that they are building tools to help
people catch up with their friends and not necessarily helping them
being constantly on top of what&#x27;s happening in their friends&#x27; lives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would say that frequent updates will help information reach people
in a timely fashion but that isn&#x27;t entirely accurate: if there was an
emergency, I would be making a phone call or use some other means of
highly real-time technology that requires absolute engagement from all
involved parties than post on social media and hope that it reaches and
grabs the attention of all concerned parties in a timely fashion.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I propose feed updates only be made in fixed durations. By updates, I
refer to downloading the posts created by the people I follow and
uploading my newly created posts to other people&#x27;s feeds. This way, we
will only be catching up with each other rather than anxiously scrolling
and constantly refreshing for new updates.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Basic needs</title>
		<published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://batsense.net/blog/03-12-2021-basic-needs/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://batsense.net/blog/03-12-2021-basic-needs/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think definition of basic needs is a little out dated. I mean, a
roof over your head, food on the table, clothes on your back and a bed
to sleep in? They sound like the needs of cattle than that of a
complexed, civilized human.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s how I would describe basic needs: the ability to pay for or
acquire decent healthcare, quality family time through vacations and
other means, and self-development(fitness classes, pottery, etc.). I&#x27;m
not saying that owning a private yacht and a personal fitness studio
should also be considered basic needs --- that&#x27;s luxury but letting
off steam once in a while and engaging in creative pursuits are all part
of a healthy, sustainable and happy life, is it not?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, this post might come off as entitled but I think if humanity is able
to meet these needs, we will be free of suffering, gleaming with joy and
have a sense of fulfilment!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Math and second systems effect</title>
		<published>2021-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://batsense.net/blog/13-09-2021-math-second-systems-effect/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://batsense.net/blog/13-09-2021-math-second-systems-effect/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think math is suffering from &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Second-system_effect&quot;&gt;second-system
effect&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Right from
7th grade onwards, kids are taught about symmetric functions and whatnot
but are rarely told where they become useful. And as years go by and as
the kid advances in school, additional baggage is added to a point where
the sole purpose of this ordeal, at least in my opinion, is to torture
the kid into oblivion.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This semester I have graph theory at school. Graph theory is one of
those things that feels like reading a quick start manual --- almost
everything taught has some &lt;em&gt;real&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and actionable purpose. Which is
pretty cool. Now this isn&#x27;t because of some magical trait of the subject
itself, it&#x27;s just that my 7th grade garbage is finally seeing some
usage. Also, it&#x27;s amazing how we spend years learning how to &lt;em&gt;read&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
math. I get it. Mathematical logic can&#x27;t have any exceptions and should
hold true in all cases. So a perfect language to describe the perfect
system. Sound familiar?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it can be argued that math has been very successful to a point where
entire fields of studies have been born out of it. But very few subjects
are as notorious as math is. Another case in favour of its complexity
is that the field is hundreds, if not thousands, of years old and the
knowledge accumulated over such a long period will be inevitably
complex. This is a valid point, but it doesn&#x27;t make the learner&#x27;s life
any easier.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, a peek into the useful aspects of math occasionally
should provide sufficient motivation to pursue its study. Mindlessly
reading specification after specification without ever understanding its
intended purpose will only serve to demotivate the learner.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could never do math. I always taught I wasn&#x27;t cut out for it and so it
has never been my thing. But this recent experience makes me wonder if
math is plagued by second-system syndrome and, at least in my case,
collapsed under its own weight.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then again, I might simply lack the lobes for it :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;



&lt;video 
  
    style=display:block;margin:auto;
  

  
  alt=&quot;lobes reference: Rom, in classic Ferengi style, tries to cheat his brother Quark and take over his bar. Any normal species would call it a betrayal and generally burn bridges but not the Ferengi. Quark is impressed by how deceitful Rom was and praises Rom: I didn&amp;#x27;t think you had the lobs&quot;
  
  controls autoplay loop muted playsinline width=&quot;350px&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;&amp;#x2F;img&amp;#x2F;blog&amp;#x2F;13-09-2021-math-second-systems-effect&amp;#x2F;firengi-meme.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video&#x2F;mp4&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;video&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
